# Xishun Liao

Los Angeles, CA, USA | Phone: (301) 742-5348 | Email: liaoxishun@gmail.com | Google Scholar | LinkedIn

## **SUMMARY**

Specializes in driver behavior modeling, prediction, multi-agent interaction, motion planning, human travel behavior modeling, and vehicle-to-everything (V2X). Implemented the proposed methodologies on both simulation platforms and real-world passenger vehicles. Experience in managing multiple projects with strict deadlines and budgetary guidelines. Published 9 journal articles, 14 conference articles, and 1 book chapter. Served as a reviewer for 13 journals and conferences.

#### **EDUCATION**

**Ph.D. in Electrical and Computer Engineering,** University of California, Riverside Apr. 2019 - Jun. 2023

Areas of Expertise: Autonomous Driving

M.E. in Mechanical Engineering, University of Maryland, College Park Jan. 2017- Dec. 2018

Areas of Expertise: Robotics

**B.E. in Mechanical Engineering and Automation,** Beijing University of Posts and Telecommunications Sep. 2012 - Jun. 2016

Areas of Expertise: Machinery Automation

## **EMPLOYMENT EXPERIENCE**

Postdoctoral Scholar, Dept. of Civil Engineering, University of California, Los Angeles Aug. 2023 - Present

Advisors: Dr. Jiagi Ma

**Research Intern,** Honda Research Institute USA, San Jose, CA

Sep. 2021 - Mar. 2022

Advisors: Dr. Teruhisa Misu and Dr. Shashank Mehrotra

Graduate Student Researcher, Dept. of Electrical and Computer Engineering, University of California, Riverside Apr. 2019 – Jun. 2023

Advisors: Dr. Guoyuan Wu and Dr. Matthew Barth

#### **RESEARCH FOCUSES**

#### **Human Behavior Study for Human-Centered Autonomy**

My research is geared towards creating an autonomy system that is deeply attuned to human needs and behaviors, leveraging the advanced capabilities of Digital Twin technology. This initiative utilizes data-driven, deep learning algorithms to refine the understanding and prediction of human driving behaviors at a micro-scale for intelligent vehicles, and to model human travel behaviors at a macro-scale for comprehensive transportation systems. Key components of the project include:

- Driver Behavior: Dedicated to model personalized driving behavior and vehicular interactions.
- Human Travel Behavior: Focused on modeling human mobility patterns across cities and diverse geographical regions.

## **Motion Planning and Decision Making for Connected and Automated Vehicles**

Focused on crafting advanced algorithms for prediction, behavior modeling, and motion planning, this initiative utilizes a custombuilt digital twin platform, encompassing both vehicle and driver digital twins. Experiments were conducted in simulated environments as well as real-world settings. Key aspects of this research include:

- Cooperative Motion Planning and Decision Making: Specializing in platooning, ramp-merging, eco-approaching, and departure strategies.
- Vehicle Trajectory Prediction
- Behavior-Aware Advanced Driving Assistance System
- Experiment platform construction: Establishing a comprehensive Vehicle-Edge-Cloud digital twin road experiment platform, alongside a versatile co-simulation platform.

## **Intelligent Transportation System**

This research adopts an AI and data-driven approach, centralizing on the integration of varied datasets to augment transportation systems.

It aims at boosting the capabilities and efficiency of transportation infrastructures through cutting-edge technological innovations. The primary areas of focus include:

- Traffic Flow Modeling and Prediction.
- Spatiotemporal and Environmental Estimation: analyzes impacts of traffic accidents and work zones on traffic dynamics.

#### **PUBLICATIONS**

#### Journal publications

[J9] Foundation Intelligence for Smart Infrastructure Services in Transportation 5.0

- Xu Han, Zonglin Meng, Xin Xia, <u>Xishun Liao</u>, Yueshuai He, Zhaoliang Zheng, Yutong Wang, Hao Xiang, Zewei Zhou
   Letian Gao, Lili Fan, Yuke Li, and Jiaqi Ma
- IEEE Transactions on Intelligent Vehicles, 2023 (Early Acess)

[J8] Driver Digital Twin for Online Prediction of Personalized Lane Change Behavior

- Xishun Liao, Xuanpeng Zhao, Ziran Wang, Zhouqiao Zhao, Kyungtae Han, Rohit Gupta, Matthew J. Barth, Guoyuan
   Wu
- IEEE Internet of Things Journal, vol. 10, no. 15, Aug. 2023, pp. 13235–13246.

[J7] A Real-World Data-Driven Approach for Estimating Environmental Impacts of Traffic Accidents

- Xishun Liao, Guoyuan Wu, Lan Yang, Matthew J. Barth
- Transportation Research Part D: Transport and Environment, vol. 117, Apr. 2023, p. 103664

[J3] Evaluating Cybersecurity Risks of Cooperative Ramp Merging in Mixed Traffic Environments

- Xuanpeng Zhao, Ahmed Abdo, Xishun Liao, Matthew J. Barth, and Guoyuan Wu
- IEEE Intelligent Transportation Systems Magazine, vol. 14, no. 6, Nov.-Dec. 2022, pp. 52-65

[J5] Game Theory-Based Ramp Merging for Mixed Traffic with Unity-SUMO Co-Simulation

- Xishun Liao, Xuanpeng Zhao, Ziran Wang, Kyungtae Han, Prashant Tiwari, Matthew J. Barth, and Guoyuan Wu
- IEEE Transactions on Systems, Man, and Cybernetics: Systems, vol. 52, no. 9, Sep. 2022, pp. 5746–5757.

[J4] Cooperative Ramp Merging Design and Field Implementation: A Digital Twin Approach Based on Vehicle-to-Cloud Communication

- Xishun Liao, Ziran Wang, Xuanpeng Zhao, Kyungtae Han, Prashant Tiwari, Matthew J. Barth, and Guoyuan Wu
- IEEE Transactions on Intelligent Transportation Systems, vol. 23, no. 5, May 2022, pp. 4490–4500

[J3] Co-Simulation Platform for Modeling and Evaluating Connected and Automated Vehicles and Human Behavior in Mixed Traffic

- Xuanpeng Zhao, Xishun Liao, Ziran Wang, Kyungtae Han, Prashant Tiwari, Matthew J. Barth, and Guoyuan Wu
- SAE International Journal of Connected and Automated Vehicles, vol. 5, no. 4, Apr. 2022

[J2] A Systematic Review of Autonomous Emergency Braking System: Impact Factor, Technology, and Performance Evaluation

- Lan Yang, Yipeng Yang, Guoyuan Wu, Xiangmo Zhao, Shan Fang, Xishun Liao, Runmin Wang, and Mengxiao Zhang
- Journal of Advanced Transportation, vol. 2022, Article ID 1188089, Apr. 2022

[J1] Driver Behavior Modeling using Game Engine and Real Vehicle: A Learning-Based Approach

- Ziran Wang, <u>Xishun Liao</u>, Chao Wang, David Oswald, Guoyuan Wu, Kanok Boriboonsomsin, Matthew J. Barth, Kyungtae Han, BaekGyu Kim, and Prashant Tiwari
- IEEE Transactions on Intelligent Vehicles, vol. 5, no. 4, Dec. 2020, pp. 738–749

#### **Conference Publications**

[C14] Deep Activity Model: A Generative Deep Learning Approach for Human Mobility Pattern Synthesis

- Brian Yueshuai He, Xishun Liao, Qinhua Jiang, Chenchen Kuai, Jiaqi Ma
- 103<sup>rd</sup> Annual Meeting of the Transportation Research Board, Washington, D.C., Jan 2024.

[C13] Inverse Reinforcement Learning and Gaussian Process Regression-based Real-time Framework for Personalized Adaptive Cruise Control

- Zhouqiao Zhao, Xishun Liao, Amr Abdelraouf, Kyungtae Han, Rohit Gupta, Matthew J. Barth, Guoyuan Wu
- 2023 IEEE 26<sup>th</sup> International Conference on Intelligent Transportation Systems (ITSC), Bilbao, Bizkaia, Spain, 2023

[C12] Improving Truck Merging at Ramps in a Mixed Traffic Environment: A Multi-human-in-the-loop (MHuiL) Approach

- Xuanpeng Zhao, Xishun Liao, Guoyuan Wu, Kanok Boriboonsomsin, Matthew J. Barth
- 2023 IEEE 26<sup>th</sup> International Conference on Intelligent Transportation Systems (ITSC), Bilbao, Bizkaia, Spain, 2023

[C11] Real-time Learning of Driving Gap Preference for Personalized Adaptive Cruise Control

- Zhouqiao Zhao, Xishun Liao, Amr Abdelraouf, Kyungtae Han, Rohit Gupta, Matthew J. Barth, Guoyuan Wu
- 2023 IEEE International Conference on Systems, Man, and Cybernetics (SMC), Honolulu, Oahu, HI, USA

[C10] Exploring Vehicular Interaction from Trajectories Based on Granger Causality

- Xishun Liao, Guoyuan Wu, Matthew J. Barth, Rohit Gupta, and Kyungtae Han
- 2023 IEEE Intelligent Vehicles Symposium (IV), Anchorage, AK, USA, 2023, pp. 1-7

[C9] Driver Digital Twin for Online Prediction of Personalized Lane Change Behavior

- Xishun Liao, Xuanpeng Zhao, Ziran Wang, Zhouqiao Zhao, Kyungtae Han, Rohit Gupta, Matthew J. Barth, and Guoyuan Wu
- 102<sup>nd</sup> Annual Meeting of the Transportation Research Board, Washington, D.C., Jan 2023.

[C8] Driver Profile Modeling Based on Driving Style, Personality Traits, and Mood States

- Xishun Liao, Shashank Mehrotra, Samson Ho, Yuki Gorospe, Xingwei Wu, and Teruhisa Mistu
- 2022 IEEE 25<sup>th</sup> International Conference on Intelligent Transportation Systems (ITSC), Macau, China, 2022, pp. 709-716.

[C7] Online Prediction of Lane Change with a Hierarchical Learning-Based Approach

- <u>Xishun Liao</u>, Ziran Wang, Xuanpeng Zhao, Zhouqiao Zhao, Kyungtae Han, Prashant Tiwari, Matthew J. Barth, and Guoyuan Wu
- 2022 International Conference on Robotics and Automation (ICRA), Philadelphia, PA, USA, 2022, pp. 948-954.

[C6] Estimating the Impacts of Automatic Emergency Braking Technology on Traffic Energy and Emissions

- Xishun Liao, Guoyuan Wu, Lan Yang, Matthew J. Barth
- 101st Annual Meeting of the Transportation Research Board, Washington, D.C., Jan 2022.

[C5] A Game Theory Based Ramp Merging Strategy for Connected and Automated Vehicles in the Mixed Traffic: A Unity-SUMO Integrated Platform

- Xishun Liao, Xuanpeng Zhao, Guoyuan Wu, Matthew J. Barth, Ziran Wang, Kyungtae Han, and Prashant Tiwari
- Transportation Research Board 100<sup>th</sup> Annual Meeting, Virtual Conference, Jan. 2021.

[C3] Cooperative Ramp Merging with Vehicle-to-Cloud Communications: A Field Experiment

- <u>Xishun Liao</u>, David Oswald, Ziran Wang, Guoyuan Wu, Kanok Boriboonsomsin, Matthew J. Barth, Kyungtae Han, BaekGyu Kim, and Prashant Tiwari
- Transportation Research Board 99th Annual Meeting, Washington D.C., Jan. 2020.

[C2] End-to-End Vision-Based Adaptive Cruise Control (ACC) Using Deep Reinforcement Learning

- Zhensong Wei, Yu Jiang, Xishun Liao, Xuewei Qi, Ziran Wang, Guoyuan Wu, Peng Hao, and Matthew J. Barth
- Transportation Research Board 99<sup>th</sup> Annual Meeting, Washington D.C., Jan. 2020.

[C1] A Digital Twin Paradigm: Vehicle-to-Cloud Based Advanced Driver Assistance Systems

- Ziran Wang, Xishun Liao, Xuanpeng Zhao, Kyungtae Han, Prashant Tiwari, Matthew J. Barth, and Guoyuan Wu
- IEEE 91<sup>st</sup> Vehicular Technology Conference (VTC2020-Spring), Virtual Conference, May 2020.

## **Book Chapter**

[B1] Driver Behavior-Aware Cooperative Ramp Merging for Intelligent Vehicles

- Xishun Liao, Xuanpeng Zhao, Ziran Wang, Matthew J. Barth, Guoyuan Wu, and Kyungtae Han
- Towards Human-Vehicle Harmonization, vol. 3, pp. 193 210, De Gruyter

## **Technical Reports**

[R2] Connectivity-Based Cooperative Ramp Merging in Multimodal and Mixed Traffic Environment

- Guoyuan Wu, Xuanpeng Zhao, Xishun Liao, Kanok Boriboonsomsin, Matthew J. Barth
- No. PSR-21-20. METRANS Transportation Center in California, 2022.

[R1] Estimating the Impacts of Automatic Emergency Braking (AEB) Technology on Traffic Energy and Emissions

- Guoyuan Wu, Xishun Liao, Lan Yang, Matthew J. Barth
- No. PSR-MT-19-26-a. Pacific Southwest Region University Transportation Center (UTC), 2021.

## **STUDY METHODOLOGIES**

**Programming and Software Tools:** Python/PyTorch, C#, C++, MATLAB, Unity, CARLA/Unreal, VISSIM, SUMO, SolidWorks, AutoCAD, Arduino, ANSYS

**Deep Learning:** Time Series (RNN/GRU/LSTM), Attention Mechanism and Transformer-based Network, Imitation Learning (IRL, GAIL, GAN), Reinforcement Learning, Graph Neural Network (GCN, GAT), Convolution-based Networks (CNN)

Machine Learning: Regression, Classification, Clustering

Control Theory: Linear/ Non-Linear Control (PID, Sliding mode), Distributed Control, Optimal Control (LQR, MPC), Fuzzy Control

Game Theory: Stackelberg Game, Nash Equilibrium, Level-k Game

Computer Vision: YOLO, R-CNN, Hough transform, Camera calibration, Feature extraction (SIFT, HOG etc.)

**Additional Technical Skills and Theories:** State and Parameter Estimation, Optimization, Motion Planning, Causality Discovery (Granger Causality), Traffic Theory, Kinematics and Dynamics Modeling, Embedded System